<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A certificate from Northampton-shire. 1. Of the pluralities. 2. Defect of maintenance. 3. Of not preaching. 4. Of scandalous ministers. As there is an order lately printed and published concerning ministers, by a committee of the high court of Parliament. Wherein every ingenuous person is desired to be very active to improve the present opportunitie, by giuing true information of all the parishes in their severall counties.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1641</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 31 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A78503</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C1766</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E163_13</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R5755</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99872895</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99872895</idno>
            <idno type="VID">156948</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A78503)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 156948)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 29:E163[13])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A certificate from Northampton-shire. 1. Of the pluralities. 2. Defect of maintenance. 3. Of not preaching. 4. Of scandalous ministers. As there is an order lately printed and published concerning ministers, by a committee of the high court of Parliament. Wherein every ingenuous person is desired to be very active to improve the present opportunitie, by giuing true information of all the parishes in their severall counties.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 20, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for William Sheares,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1641.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Clergy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Patronage, Ecclesiastical --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Northamptonshire (England) --  History --  Sources --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles I, 1625-1649 --  Sources --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:156948:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:156948:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A CERTIFICATE FROM <hi>NORTHAMP<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TON</hi>-SHIRE.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>Of the Pluralities.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>Defect of Maintenance.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. <hi>Of not Preaching.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4. <hi>Of ſcandalous Miniſters.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>As there is an Order lately printed and publiſhed concerning Miniſters, by a Committee of the high Court of Parliament.</p>
            <p>Wherein every Ingenuous perſon is deſired to be very active to improve the preſent opportunitie, by giuing true information of all the Pariſhes in their ſeverall Counties.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>William Sheares.</hi> 1641.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:156948:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:156948:2"/>
            <head>A CERTIFICATE from <hi>Northampton</hi>-ſhire;</head>
            <head type="sub">1. Touching Pluralities, 2. Defect of main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance. 3. Of not Preaching. 4. Of ſcandalous Miniſters.</head>
            <head> For <hi>Northampton</hi>-ſhire.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His is to certifie, that for plurali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties there is not in the whole Shire above ſixteene or twentie the number of Benefices being 326. as they are reckoned by <hi>Cambden</hi> and <hi>Speed.</hi> And it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by ſome of good judgement, that theſe few pluralities doe nothing ſo much hinder the preaching of the Goſpell, and diſcharge of their duties in ſeverall kindes, as doe the poore and ſcandalous livings in the Countrey, which I thinke in number are about one halfe almoſt one hundred and fiftie.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Francis Bacon</hi> in his conſiderations for Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralities ſaith, that in caſe the number of able Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters were ſufficient, and the value of the Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:156948:3"/>were ſufficient, then Pluralities were in no ſort tolerable, but take wee heed that we deſire not contraries, for to deſire that every Pariſh ſhould be furniſhed with a ſufficient Preacher, and to deſire that pluralities be forthwith taken away, is to deſire things contrary; conſidering <hi>de facto</hi> there are not ſufficient Preachers for every pariſh whereto adde that there is not ſufficient mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance in many pariſhes to maintaine a Preacher which makes the impoſſibility ſo much the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
            <p>Let me adde hereunto one paſſage of the ſame Author.</p>
            <p>For my owne opinion I muſt confeſſe, let mee ſpeake it with reverence, that all the Parliaments ſince the 27. and 31. of K. <hi>Henry</hi> the 8. who gave away Impropriations from the Church ſeeme to me to ſtand in ſome ſort obnoxious, and obliged to God in conſcience to doe ſomewhat for the Church to reduce the patrimony thereof to a competency, for ſince they have debarred Chriſts wife of a great part of her dowry, it were reaſon they made her a competent joyncture.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To the ſecond inquiry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Touching want of maintenance, or little main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance the particulars are very many. For one halfe almoſt are appropriate Churches, and the Vicarages commonly left ſo ſmall and deſtitute, that there is no ſufficient meanes left to a Miniſter to buy Bookes, nor to keepe hoſpitality, or live like a Miniſter in reaſonable condition. Beſides
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:156948:3"/>the Vicarages that are poore, there are many Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonagee ſo abridged and ſpoyled under pretence of long Leaſes made before the Statute, and alſo rate tithes in lieu of tithes in kinde, that the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings are poore and ſcandalous. And it is thought by ſome, that theſe poore livings being ſo many for number, doe more hinder the preaching of the Goſpell, then the few Pluralities, becauſe the puraliſts doe preach by themſelves, and their Curates, and doe oftentimes write in defence of the truth, but the Impropriators preach not at all, poore Vicars preach perhaps more ſeldome then otherwiſe they would, and ſome not at all. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides pluralities are not held ſucceſſively ſo, which is very conſiderable, but poore Vicarages are continued without amendment. As to inſtance in particulars.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Parſonage of <hi>Piddington</hi> in the Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred of <hi>Wimmerſley</hi> diſtant three miles from <hi>Northampton,</hi> is worth almoſt three hundred pounds yearely, which Sir <hi>Iohn Wake</hi> Knight de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines wholly in his hands, enjoying both the Parſonage houſe, all the glebe, being three or foure yard land, together with all the tithes what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever. And there is not ſo much as a poore Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate left reſident there to reade prayers, or Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſe, or bury the dead, or any ſuch like duty. On<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> keepes a Miniſter in his houſe at the Lodge in <hi>Sawcy</hi> Forreſt, whom he ſends to <hi>Pid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dington</hi> at times. There lived lately one Maſter <hi>Cave</hi> a very poore miſerable Miniſter, in a very poore Cottage for the ſpace of ſome forty yeares,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:156948:4"/>and after his death ſome three or foure yeares a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goe there was a Curate one <hi>Durham,</hi> then one <hi>Langley,</hi> and now one <hi>Setterford,</hi> who uncertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſerve the cure in a very poore manner, being not inſtituted nor inducted, neither is there one child or ſervant in the pariſh that can ſay the Lords prayer of their teaching: though the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh conſiſts of another Village <hi>(Hackelton)</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyning to it, ſo that the Inhabitants are many in number.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Iohn Wake</hi> holds the Parſonage (as is reported) by colour of ſome old Leaſe from S <hi>Iohns</hi> Hoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall in <hi>Northampton,</hi> which Leaſe whether it ſhall expire ever or never is uncertaine to any neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour. Whatſoever his Leaſe or title be, it is very fit he ſhould allow 100. pounds yearely, together with the dwelling houſe to a reſident Miniſter, with a convenient portion of the glebe land; it being no lawfull Uicarage, but a Church robbed by ſtrong hand.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Parſonage of <hi>Hartnell,</hi> not farre of, is worth about 100. pounds yearely, and is held by Sir <hi>Iohn Wake,</hi> in the ſame kind; the poore Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter Maſter <hi>Io: Gittins</hi> that doth ſerve the Cure, is ſo very poore and miſerable, that no marvell, there is no preaching, he hath beene there ſome thirty or forty yeares.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Parſonage of <hi>Horton</hi> diſtant three or foure miles from <hi>Northampton</hi> is alſo a poore Church, not preſentative of late yeares, (though
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:156948:4"/>not long ſince it was) but being incloſed wholly in paſtures, and lately come into the hands of a great Nobleman <hi>(the Lord Privy Seale)</hi> there is a ſtipendiary Curate allowed at ſome meane rate; but no man dare be bold to call it in queſtion, the neighbours being but of meane condition that dare not complaine, whatſoever their loſſe or grievance be.</p>
            <p>The Curate is one maſter <hi>Marten,</hi> of commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable deſart, for ought I know, and lives there by curteſie in an—</p>
            <p>But the Parſonage houſe, glebe and tithes are all loſt and gone, for ought I can heare.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The Vicarage of <hi>Preſton</hi> diſtant three miles from <hi>Northampton,</hi> is worth 100. markes yearely, as is reported, but the dwelling houſe is long ſince pulled downe, the glebe loſt, and the tithes all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by the Lords of the Mannour, Sir <hi>Robert Hartnell</hi> and his Father, allowing ſome eight pounds ſtipend to a poore Vicar. Thus it conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued all Queene <hi>Elizabeths</hi> time, and King <hi>Iames</hi> raigne in a very ſcandalous manner, inſomuch as maſter <hi>Iaſper Hartnell,</hi> and Sir <hi>Robert Hartnell</hi> his ſonne, pulled downe the body of the Church, ſold the Lead and the Bells, and imployed it to prophane uſes, the Chancell alſo for a time was prophaned, being made a Kennell for Grey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hounds, and the Steeple a Pigeon houſe. As for prayers and preaching, when they were diſpoſed to have any, it was performed in the Hall or Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, the houſe ſtanding neere to the Church, and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:156948:5"/>ſometimes they frequented the Lectures at <hi>Northampton.</hi> But Sir <hi>Robert Hartnell</hi> lately ſold the whole eſtate which hee had left remaining to Sir <hi>Clement Edmonds</hi> Knight, whoſe ſonne Mr. <hi>Charles Edmond</hi> hath repaited the Chancell, and the body of the Church, and deſtroyed the Pigeons, pulling downe their neſts, and hath put all things in good order for the Church and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brick, only thee poore U<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>car is deſtitute of globe or dwelling houſe, and for theſe 80. yeares it hath ſtood in a miſerable caſe, though upon a late ſuit in th'E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>chequer, the Vicarage tithes are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered, and upon the next avoydance it is hoped there will be ſome amendment.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The Vicarage of <hi>Thrip,</hi> within three miles of <hi>Northampton</hi> is very poore and contemptible, having only a beggarly Cottage allowed to the Vicar for his dwelling houſe, and ſome ſmall tithes, to the value of 20 pounds yearely, or ſomewhat better if they bee well payd, but the Parſonage houſe, and glebe which by right, and the old indowment (which lately remained up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Record) doth belong to the Vicar, is detained by Sir <hi>Richard Samuel</hi> Knight, not by any good title in law, but ſome colour of an Order (as is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported) in th'Exchequer made long agoe, when his Grandfather perhaps was an Auditor in th'Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer, and ſo might procure ſome favour there in his owne behalfe, more then a poore miſerable Vicar could ever get reverſed or altered. The tithe corne is worth one hundred pounds yearly,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:156948:5"/>which alſo Sir <hi>Richard Samwell</hi> holdeth an Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriation.</p>
            <p>But by this meanes the Vicar is very poore, and in part ſcandalous, being a man choſen by Sir <hi>William Samwell,</hi> and there preſented, who would be ſure to place one in the Vicarage, that for want of wit and meanes, ſhould neuer be able to make any queſtion of the Parſonage houſe and glebe. The want of bread and drinke in his owne houſe, doth make him too often frequent the Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe, where if he talke fooliſhly, it is not much to be wondered at.</p>
            <p n="6">6 The Parſonage of <hi>Lampert,</hi> diſtant foure miles from <hi>Northampton,</hi> is worth about 400 pounds yearely, but it is held by Sir <hi>Iohn Iſſam</hi> Knight by colour of an old long Leaſe, and the preſent incumbent hath but ſome ſtipend upon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement, but hee-hath alſo another Living not farre off, where he reſideth, but if this Rectory had the rights reſtored, it would give entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to any one of the moſt eminent Divines in either Univerſities, and there might be continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all preaching in very due manner, with great hoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitality and reliefe of the poore. The old Curate Maſter <hi>Bunny,</hi> who dyed lately, lived very poore and long, and no marvell if there were little preaching, and 'tis pitty that ſuch a great Living ſhould be ſwallowed up under colour only of a Leaſe.</p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>Duſton</hi> a poore Vicarage ſtipendiary neere
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:156948:6"/>
               <hi>Northampton</hi> Maſter <hi>Iames</hi> the Vicaris well repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, but his living is very poore, only 20. pounds yearely, ſome 5. pounds more was given lately by the Honourable Earle of <hi>Warwicke,</hi> but he having ſold his eſtate there, that Exhibition is diſconti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued.</p>
            <p n="8">8. <hi>Dallington</hi> a poore Vicarage neere <hi>North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hampton,</hi> the Patron is Sir <hi>Henry Wallop.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are many other poore Vicarages and Livings in this Countrey, occaſioned ſometimes by the Appropriations, ſometimes by the meane and ſmall rates which in many places are given only for tithes, as twenty ſhillings where twenty pounds were due, if tithes in kind were paid. I think the Clergie would be content to forgo their pluralities (being ſo few for the number) if the poore Vicarages, and other poore livings might be made competible, or enjoy their fulltithes, and the ſmall rates taken away throughout the whole Kingdome, which is but a very reaſonable pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſall, if pluralities ſhould be taken away, and till there be a tolerable maintenance provided in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry pariſh, it is impoſſible that there ſhould be a conſtant faithfull preaching miniſtery throughout the whole kingdome, which hath beene ſo often moved and petitioned for in Parliament.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cambden</hi> doth reckon almoſt the one halfe of the pariſhes in the Kingdome to bee Vicarages, there being in the whole nine thouſand two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, whereof almoſt foure thouſand are Appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priate
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:156948:6"/>Churches, which for the moſt part are poore, beſides alſo many Parſonages are very de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute, and unfit to give entertainment to a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant and diligent Preacher, and many alſo are ſhamefully ſpoyled and robbed moſt unjuſtly, though they be not Appropriate.</p>
            <p>It hath beene reported that it was once voted in Parliament in Queene <hi>Elizabeths</hi> time, that an Act might paſſe to make it lawfull for them that would bee willing to reſtore Impropriations to the Church, (which now is not lawfull in an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary way without charge) and that the Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Earle of <hi>Huntington</hi> offered to reſtore all the Impropiations of his eſtate, which then was great, and might have many in it. The motion was in many reſpects Chriſtian, pious, and very religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, but it happened to be denyed, <hi>ne res tranſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret in exemplum;</hi> Which was deteſtable, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps one cauſe why God hath given no better ſucceſſe to many Parliaments ſince that time. Maſter <hi>Calvin</hi> ſpeaking of Impropriations, ſaith, that the theft is ſtill continued in the Church, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the theeves are changed, heretofore the Monks and Friers were the theeves, now many that would be accounted good Proteſtants. It were much to bee wiſhed that the Parliament would make an Act, whereby it ſhould be freely lawfull, and abſolutely cleere in Law, without any hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance to reſtore or purchaſe Impropriations to the Church, wherein of late yeares many worthy Gentlemen have given ſingular good example, as Maſter <hi>Richard Knightly,</hi> who dyed lately, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:156948:7"/>
               <hi>Preston</hi> and <hi>Fauſtey</hi> (as is reported) whiles he lived, bleſſed be his name and memory. I have heard a wiſe man propoſe a courſe, how the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of Impropriations might be made eaſie; and that was, if the King would bee pleaſed to publiſh and grant Letter, Patents, to give leave for reſtitution of them, and if this may hold good in law, (as good Lawyers may eaſily informe and direct a courſe, for the drawing of the Letters Patents) it would in time produce many ſingular and good effects, for many well diſpoſed Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men are willing to reſtore, and many might bee named, as Sir william <hi>Dorrington,</hi> Knight of Hampſhire, reſtored ſix out of his owne eſtate, to the value of five hundred pounds yearely, and more.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning the ſcarcity of preaching Miniſters throughout the whole Kingdome.</head>
               <p>In the generall it may be objected, that there is no ſcarcity, for it is thought, and I take it, may eaſily bee proved, that for number there are more Preachers, and for worth and deſert more excellent within theſe laſt 40. yeares, then ever was ſince the Reformation of Religion, or ſince we were firſt Chriſtians. And both the Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities have greatly encreaſed in numbers of Schol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers and Preachers, eſpecially ſince King <hi>Iames</hi> his time becauſe he gave ſo pious example, being excellently learned himſelfe, and ſpeaking favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably, as the good <hi>Hezekias</hi> did to all the Levites,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:156948:7"/>that taught the good knowledge of the Lord.</p>
               <p>Perhaps the ſcarcity of preaching Miniſters (if it be ſo) may ariſe from the cauſes alledged in the Conference at <hi>Hampton</hi> Court.— Where the King ſaith that he had conſulted with his Biſhops about that complaint, whom hee found willing and ready to ſecond him in it, — but as <hi>ſubita e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vacutio,</hi> was <hi>periculoſa,</hi> ſo <hi>ſubita mutatio,</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this matter was not for a preſent reſolution, becauſe to appoint to every pariſh a ſufficient Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, were impoſſible, the Univerſities would not afford them. Againe, hee had found already that he had more learned men in his Realme then he had ſufficient maintenance for, ſo that mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance muſt firſt be provided, and then the other to be required. What the King ſaith that the U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſities will not afford ſtore of learned Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers to ſupply every pariſh throughout the Kingdome, is true, if a view and conſideration be taken of their numbers; for both Univerſities will not afford conſtantly every yeare 200. Preachers (though perhaps at this inſtant they would afford 100. a piece, becauſe there bee many there that would gladly bee gone if they had Benefices) whereas of nine thouſand pariſhes, and 200. in all, there dyes five or ſix hundred Miniſters every yeare, ſo that there ſhould be to ſupply the vacan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies that happen by death every yeare ſo many ready Preachers (if the Colledges could afford them) but ſeeing the Univerſities cannot afford ſo many, the ſupply of the reſt (300. at leaſt year<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) muſt come from Curates, Schoole-maſters,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:156948:8"/>and ſuch as teach children in the houſes of Knights and Gentlemen, whom they commonly reward with ſome Benefice in their gift and dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>But further in that Conference of <hi>Hampton</hi> Court, Doctor <hi>Bilſon</hi> then Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> made knowne to the King that then inſufficiencie of the Clergie, be it as it was at that time, came not by the Biſhops defaults, but partly by Lay-Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons, who did preſent very meane men to their Cures, whereof in himſelfe he ſhewed an inſtance, how that ſince his being Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> very few Maſters of Art, were preſented to good Benefices, partly by the law of the Land, which admitteth of very meane and tolerable ſufficiency in any Clerkes, ſo that if the Biſhop ſhould not admit them, then preſently a <hi>Quare impedit</hi> is ſent out againſt him. And certainly it cannot bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed but that man. Patrons are very much to bee blamed, for as the excellent Biſhop <hi>Iewel</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained in his time, in a Sermon before the Queenes Majeſty, that if the Patron were no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then a Gentleman, they ſeldome ſuffer a Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to paſſe, but either for the Leaſe, or for ready money. I wiſh it were made by Law to be felo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, to take either Leaſe of the tithes or ready mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney for a Living. Mr. <hi>George Catesby</hi> Gentleman, that wants neither wit nor learning, and one that will talke zealouſly for Religion, yet he ſold moſt ſhamefully a very good Parſonage, <hi>viz. Acton</hi> worth 240 pounds yearely, firſt to one Maſter <hi>Carjer,</hi> then to one Maſter <hi>Parker,</hi> two ſcandalous
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:156948:8"/>Miniſters for many diſorders, ſo that Maſter <hi>Cateſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by</hi> was the true cauſe of that ſcandall and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe that did ariſe to the Church thereby, and now the ſame Living is upon ſale againe the third time, the old incumbent being hurt and ſickly. But when Benefices are expoſed to ſale, the choyce of a Miniſter can never be good, for Chapmen that buy in this kind are commonly obnoxious men, or none of the beſt ſort.</p>
               <p>Maſter <hi>Perkins,</hi> that man of God, in his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon of the duties and dignity of the miniſtery, giveth three reaſons of the rareneſſe and ſcarce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of good Miniſters. 1. The contempt and diſgrace of their Calling, by wicked and worldly men. 2. The difficulty of diſcharging the duties of their Calling. 3. The third is more peculiar to this age of the New Teſtament, <hi>viz.</hi> Want of maintenance and preferment for men that labour in the Calling, and that in theſe times under the Goſpell, when it deſerves beſt to bee rewarded. Certainly it were a worthy Chriſtian policy to propound good preferments to this Calling, that thereby men of the worthieſt gifts might be wonne to it, and the want thereof is the cauſe why ſo many young men, of eſpeciall parts and greateſt hope, runne to other vocations, and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially to the Law, wherein at this day the greateſt part of the fineſt wits of the Kingdome are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed. And why? but becauſe they have all the meanes to riſe, whereas the Miniſtery for the moſt part yeeldeth nothing but a plaine way to begge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. This is a great blemiſh in our Church, and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:156948:9"/>ſurely I wiſh the Papiſts, thoſe children of this world, were not wiſer in their kind, in this point, then the Church of God. The reformation here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is a worke worthy of the labour of a Prince and people, and ſpeciall care is to be had in it, elſe it will not bee reformed, for doubtleſſe had not God himſelfe in the Old Teſtament taken ſuch ſtreight order for the Livings of the Levites, they had beene put to no leſſe extremities, then is the Miniſtery of this Age. Thus maſter <hi>Perkins,</hi> and much more he hath touching this and the former reaſons, in the ſame Treatiſe, whereto I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre.</p>
               <p>It is not to be forgotten, what was the ſinne of <hi>Ierobeam,</hi> that made <hi>Iſrael</hi> to ſinne, hee made Prieſts of the baſeſt of the people; and this hee did,
<note place="margin">2 Chron. 13.9.</note> becauſe he robbed ſacrilegiouſly the Prieſts and Levites of all the Cities which they had in his Kingdome of the ten Tribes, (and thoſe Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties were many more then there are Biſhopricks in <hi>England.</hi>) And alſo he freed the people from the payment of tithes to the Levites (which is the ſecret thing which our common Freeholders and Grand-Iury-men doe ſo much ayme at, if Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and their Courts were overthrowne) ſo that of neceſſity he muſt make baſe Prieſts, for his baſe gods. And ſo if tithes were taken away here, then would quickly follow <hi>Ierobeams</hi> Prieſthood baſe, contemptible, poore and illiterate, for what man of good quality or ability, will bring up his ſonne to the Miniſtery, when he ſhall be ſure to be nayled faſt to one place, and live there only upon
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:156948:9"/>a ſtipend.— <hi>Invitatus ad haec aliquis de ponte negabit;</hi> A beggars brat taken from the bridge where he ſits a begging, if he knew the inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience had cauſe to refuſe it.</p>
               <p>But I greatly hope, and truſt that God will ſo direct and bleſſe the ſupreme Court of Iuſtice, that they will be ready to command, double Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to be given to the labouring Clergy, as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> requireth, and make the Calling honourable and reſpected, according to the true eſteeme that it ought to have. God ſaid anciently, <hi>Levit.</hi> 21.8. <hi>Thou ſhalt ſanctifie the Prieſt, and hee ſhall be holy to thee.</hi> 1. Thou ſhalt reverently eſteeme him as an holy perſon.—<hi>Calvin</hi> ſaith upon the place,— <hi>Quo melius commendet ſacri officii reverentiam ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monet ad totius populi ſalutem ſpectare; Ego, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit, ſum Deus qui ves ſanctifico: Illis autem ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis ſignificat gratiam adoptionis, qua ſelecti erant in peculium, in ſacerdotio fundatam eſſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And now perhaps you will expect to know from whom this commeth, which for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, I muſt requeſt you to excuſe; becauſe I feare that upon the knowledge of my name, ſo many perſons as I have had occaſion to taxe, will thinke that I ſingled them out of envie and malice, which I utterly deny: whereas I might have inſiſted up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on many more in the like kind offending: it is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed too true, there are many more, but hoping there will be a vigilant eye, and prudent care car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried in examining the truth of all things, and that many others will ſend in their Advertiſements to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:156948:10"/>the like purpoſe, I will proceed no further. Only ſubmitting to cenſure whatſoever is amiſſe, and ſhall be glad if any thing here mentioned may give the leaſt furtherance to the advancement of Gods glory.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Only let me adde one thing as a poſtſcript.</head>
               <p>Whereas there is a bruite and rumour ſpread, that the Clergy is over-growne of late; and as I have heard it was ſo told unto the King, when he was laſt at <hi>Barwicke,</hi> by Maſter <hi>Henderſon,</hi> a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall Scottiſh Miniſter, and alſo among our owne ſelves many doe thinke ſo, yet I take it under cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection to be a notorious errour and fallacie. Sir <hi>Francis Bacon</hi> ſaith in one of his Eſſayes, That it is to be foreſeene that the population of a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome (eſpecially if it bee not mowne downe by Warres) doe not exceed the ſtocke of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, which ſhould maintaine them, neither is the population to be reckoned only by number, for a ſmaller number that ſpend more, and earne leſſe, doe weare out an Eſtate ſooner, than a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter number, that live lower and gather more, therefore the multiplying of Nobility, and other degrees of Quality, in an over-proportion to the common people, doth ſpeedily bring a ſtate to neceſſitie. Hee doth hereby intimate not obſcure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that our Nobility and Gentry is greatly over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>growne, for whereas there was but ſome ſeven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene Earles, and twenty ſixe Barons in <hi>Hen.</hi> 8.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:156948:10"/>time, before the diſſolution of Religious houſes, now there is encreaſed a very great number more eſpecially ſince the beginning of King <hi>Iames,</hi> who to reward old ſervants, and gaine new friends, and withall perhaps to weaken the power and greatneſſe of the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, encreaſed their number exceedingly, eſpecially both before in the Queenes time, and <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. they did riſe upon the Church lands and poſſeſſions, being ſeated for the moſt part up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Abbeys, and ſuch like houſes taken from Biſhops and Churches. Whereas if the lands and poſſeſſions of the Abbeyes had beene well imployed, as was pretended and projected, they would have made the Crowne richer then the Crowne of <hi>Spaine</hi> and both the <hi>Indies.</hi> For the yearely Revenue of theſe lands comes to foure millions ſterling, according to the improved rents of this Age, whereof if but a third or fourth part had beene annexed to the Crowne and fixed, there would have beene little need to grant Subſidies. Whereas being uſed as it happened, it enriched the Crowne very little, but rayſed a number of petty fog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, and many new Gentlemen, <hi>as Raleigh ſpeaketh.</hi> And it is eaſie to bee obſerved, that whereas in Queene <hi>Elizabeths</hi> time, there was but two or three Knights in the Shire, now there is ſixtie, beſides many pretended Eſquires and Gentlemen, which as <hi>Bacon</hi> ſaith, doe
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:156948:11"/>ſpend much, and earne little, living for moſt part above their quality and degree, which they ought to keepe in all their behaviour, expences, apparell, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But the Clergy for number are not much above the nine thouſand and two hundred Benefices that are in the whole Kingdome, and out of thoſe that are above that number the vacancies by death yearely muſt be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed, as Curates, Lecturers, Schoole-maſters which are beſides thoſe in the Univerſities, which will not afford conſtantly and yearely two hundred Miniſters, whereas there is about ſixe hundred vacancies in the yeare by death; and other caſualties. Beſides, the Curates which are under ſuperiour Miniſters to aſſiſt and helpe them, doe live and are maintained out of the profits of the Incumbent of the place, without charge to the Common-wealth otherwiſe, or the Pariſhes where they live, and oft times they helpe themſelves by teaching ſchoole.</p>
               <p>But if ſome ſevere courſes now voiced bee put in execution, there will be ſuch diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement given to Schollers in the Vniverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, that few will apply themſelves to the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery, there may be a <hi>ſi quis</hi> ſet up in <hi>Pauls,</hi> to accept Livings, as was done in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Queenes time, when many popiſh Prieſts did flye the Land, and the Vniverſities
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:156948:11"/>afforded no choyce and ſupply.</p>
               <p>But if the over-growing of the Clergy be underſtood of wealth and meanes, I take it is eaſie to diſprove it, for it cannot appeare upon good enquirie, that of all the Biſhops for theſe laſt eightie yeares ſince the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> that any almoſt hath left five hundred pounds yearely in land, or any ſuch conſiderable eſtate, except only very few, two or three perhaps, or that all the Biſhops being reckoned together, have not left ſo much land as one Lawyer did to his children, <hi>viz.</hi> Sir <hi>Edward Cooke,</hi> who left twenty thouſand pounds yearely, or little leſſe; Serjeant <hi>Gaudy,</hi> left five thouſand; Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeant <hi>Crew,</hi> left foure thouſand; and many Lawyers doe commonly leave one thouſand and five hundred pounds yearely, that are of ordinary practiſe, not of the principall Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell to the King, nor great Serjeants or Jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, many of whom have raiſed up great Families of Nobility and Gentry, whereas very few of the Biſhops have beene able to leave their ſonnes ſuch eſtates, as to raiſe them to Knighthood; one Biſhop <hi>Sands</hi> in Queene <hi>Elizabeths</hi> time, left his ſonnes of good eſtate, but hee was a Gentleman well deſcended, and what other meanes and helpes he had I know not, but the Queene did favour his ſonnes being worthy men. And ſome
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:156948:12"/>other Biſhops at this day, and formerly have had rich friends, by whom they have gained the greateſt part of their wealth, and not by their preferments in the Church.</p>
               <p>And for the ordinary Clergy, I doe not know any man in the Dioceſſe, that is able to leave one hundred pounds, nor ſcarce fiftie pounds to his children in land, excepting Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor <hi>Clerke,</hi> who having beene the Kings Chaplain twenty yeares hath perhaps gotten ſomething, and he that cannot leave fortie pounds or fiftie pounds in land at his death, is not to be regarded as a rich man, whereas there are many Attorneyes, beſides Lawyers, that have one hundred pounds yearely. I am ſure there dye every yeare many Miniſters very poore, and leave their children meanly provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for, in regard all the better ſort live and continue long at the Univerſities before they be preferred and married, and dye before they can gather any wealth or eſtate. And of theſe examples it is eaſie to produce an hundred for one, that leaves any thing of moment.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
